Guide to the William Klenz papers, 1944-1965 UA.29.02.0123
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Klenz papers
1944-1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Klenz, William
UA.29.02.0123
2.0 Linear Feet
William Klenz was an associate professor in Duke University's Department of Aesthetics, Art, and Music from 1947-1966. Collection contains sheet music and an unpublished manuscript by William Klenz entitled The Elements of Music Theory, 1960. A later addition from Klenz's mentee and collaborator, Geoffrey Simon, contains manuscripts for Pacem in Terris, a cantata for mixed voices and organ (dated 1965), as well as an original performing score for Toccata ("Carillon"), dedicated to Simon (dated 1959 and 1962).
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The William Klenz papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1987. An addition was received as a gift from Geoffrey Simon in 2021.
Biographical/Historical note
William Klenz was an associate professor in Duke University's Department of Aesthetics, Art and Music from 1947-1966. He was a graduate of the Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill where he received a B.M. and a B.A. respectively. He was on the staff of Music Department of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill from 1938-1942. He made numerous public appearances in North Carolina and has appeared as soloist in the in the North Carolina Symphony Orchestra. During World War II Klenz played public recitals and made radio appearances in London and Paris. Upon his return from Europe he studied with Paul Hindemith at Yale. His compositions have been performed at Smith College, Princeton and New York, as well as abroad. Publications include "G.M. Bononcin" Duke University Press, Oct. 1962, and also entries in "Encyclopedia of Music."
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of manuscript music and sheet music composed by Klenz, as well as supporting materials for some of the performances and some background information and a personal characterization of Klenz. The unpublished manuscript of William Klenz entitled The Elements of Music Theory, 1960, was donated to the Archives by a former student of Klenz.
The 2021 accession contains two additional manuscripts: first, Pacem in Terris, cantata for mixed voices and organ. Texts for Pacem in Terris were selected by Klenz from biblical and rabbinical texts cited by Rabbi Everett Gendler in his The Revolutionary Truism (The Saturday Review, February 13, 1965). The first performance of Pacem in Terris was conducted by Geoffrey Simon at American University (Washington, DC) on November 21, 1965. The material consists of the original manuscript, including an additional Intermezzo not in first manuscript; also contains one performing copy from premiere; one copy (scored in Sibelius) from a later performance; and one copy of program from the premiere.
Also donated in 2021 was an original performing score (copy of manuscript) of Toccata ("Carillon"), for organ, V-19-1959. This score was dedicated to the donor (see final page with Klenz signature, date, and "for G.S."). Its first performance was in Berlin, Germany, at the Neutempelhof Kirche on August 18, 1962.
Related Material
Dept. of Music video and sound recordings, circa 1940-1990.
University Archives, Duke University.
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives, Duke University.
Music in universities and colleges; Music -- Instruction and study; Sheet music; North Carolina Symphony; Duke University. Department of Music; Duke University -- Faculty; Simon, Geoffrey
- Sheet music, 1944-1963
  - Only for Me, Mark van Doren and John Duke, undated (Box 2)
  - Psalm 137 (Book of Common Prayer), William Klenz, undated (Box 2)
  - Shrovetide Swallow, Helen Bevington and William Klenz, undated (Box 2)
  - Song of Orphens, Helen Bevington and William Klenz, undated (Box 2)
  - Palmetto Town, William Klenz, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Le Pont Mirabeau, 1948 (Box 2)
  - O, It Was Out By Donnycarney, John Duke, Northampton, 1953 (Box 2)
  - How Goes the Night for J.H., William Klenz, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Como, Robert Nathan and William Klenz, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Hush, Robert Nathan and William Klenz, 1959 (Box 2)
  - The Peddler, Robert Nathan and William Klenz, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Meditation at a Stop Light, Mildred Weston and William Klenz, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Walk the Silver Night, Helen Bevington and William Klenz, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Easter Music in the Duke Chapel, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Unknown (Box 2)
- Manuscripts, 1959-1965
  - The Elements of Music Theory, manuscript, 1960; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Pacem in Terris, manuscripts and program, 1965; 2 Files (Box 3)
  - Toccata ("Carillon") for organ, 1959 (Box 3)